Guide to the Emma Joy Dana Collection of Artuš Scheiner
Yale University Arts Library
Emma Joy Dana Collection of Artuš Scheiner
1914-1933
AOB 30
Yale University Arts Library
0.25
1 box
The collection consists of 24 illustrations by the Czech artist Artuš Scheiner.
Dana, Emma Joy
Scheiner, Artuš, 1863-1938
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The illustrations are arranged by date of creation, as inferred from the publication date of the text in which each is reproduced. When multiple illustrations from the collection were made for the same text, these are included in a single folder in the order they appear within the published work.
Biographical / Historical
Artuš Scheiner (1863-1938) was born October 28, 1863, in Benešov in former Bohemia.1 He is best known for his children's book illustrations, though he did not begin creating art for this genre until later in life. His first children's illustrations were published in Růženka a Bobeš by Václav Říha (pseudonym Václav Tille) in 1902. Scheiner worked extensively with Říha on a series of stories that center on and are titled after female heroines.2 The author with whom Scheiner published the most works was Marta Voleská. The two created over sixty booklets to advertise the detergent company Firma Otta. In addition, Scheiner and Voleská partnered on the Kulihrášek and Tintilin series. Both series follow the adventures of a young boy in a bright red cap and are graphically distinguished by their inclusion of multiple images on a single page. Scheiner's paintings also accompany the stories of Božena Němcová, Julius Zeyer, Karel Jaromir Erben, and Hans Christian Andersen.
Beyond his children's illustrations, Scheiner made many other artistic contributions. During the late-nineteenth century his art was published primarily in magazines and in German-language novels. He first published his work in 1887 in Světozor, a weekly magazine published in Prague. From 1891 to 1906 he contributed regularly to Lustige Blätter, a weekly satirical magazine published in Berlin.3 Likely because the artist's older brother, Josef, was the President of the Czechoslovakian Sokol Association, Artuš also made drawings for gymnastics exercise books.4 In the 1890s Artuš designed a marionette theater for his brother's family that was used for weekly performances until 1907.5 The designs were presented in Loutkové divadlo Artuše Scheinera ("The Marionette Theatre of Artuš Scheiner") published by Josef R. Vilímek.
Artuš Scheiner died December 20, 1938, at the age of seventy five.
1Jana Bačovská, "Pohádková Typologie v Secesní Knižní Ilustraci," (Master's Thesis, Masaryk University, 2008), 189. 2These stories have since been grouped as "Říhovy Pohádky" or "Pohádky o Princeznách." 3Bačovská, 189. 4For instance, Bílé kroužky: Cvičení pro dorostenky [pro] XI. všesokolský slet v Praze 1948. 5Jaroslav Blecha, "The History and Scenographic Influence of Czech Family Marionette Theatres," Theatralia, 14 no. 1 (2011): 128-129.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 24 illustrations by the Czech artist Artuš Scheiner. The works consist primarily of gouache paintings for children's literature published in the early-twentieth century. Particularly well represented in this collection are illustrations for Václav Říha 's fairytales, including Lada (1918), Maruška (1918), Dvě Maričky (1920), Mariana (1920), Růženka (1920), Berona (1921), and Lidka (1921).
Custodial History
Gift of Emma Joy Dana.
Children's literature -- Illustrations; Illustration of books -- Czechoslovakia -- 20th Century; gouaches (paintings); Scheiner, Artuš, 1863-1938; Dana, Emma Joy
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Tři zlaté vlasy děda Vševěda, 1914 (Box 1)
  Separated Materials
  Tři zlaté vlasy děda Vševěda
  http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/7431228
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Tři zlaté vlasy děda Vševěda, 1914; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Lada, 1918; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Lada, 1918; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration for Maruška, 1918; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Dvě Maričky, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
  Dvě Maričky
  http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/7431399
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Dvě Maričky, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Mariana, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Mariana, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 3] for Růženka, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [2 of 3] for Růženka, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [3 of 3] for Růženka, 1920; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Berona, 1921; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Berona, 1921; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Lidka, 1921; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Lidka, 1921; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration for Chodské povídky a pohádky - řada II, 1922; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration [1 of 2] for Dub a slavík a jiné povídky, 1923; 1 (Box 1)
  General
  Illustration for the short story "O dobrodružném čápu" within the anthology.
  Caption
  "… a rozepjav svá křídla vznesl se do výše, až zmizel z lesy."
- Illustration [2 of 2] for Dub a slavík a jiné povídky, 1923; 1 (Box 1)
  Illustration for the short story "O pravém přátelství" within the anthology.
  "'Nejsem povinen vykládati vám své názory o přátelství!' zvolal urputně starý samotář."
- Illustration [1 of 3] for Pohádky bez princezen, 1929; 1 (Box 1)
  Illustration for the short story "Dědičná kovárna" within the anthology.
- Illustration [2 of 3] for Pohádky bez princezen, 1929; 1 (Box 1)
  Illustration for the short story "Vrbová žena" within the anthology.
- Illustration [3 of 3] for Pohádky bez princezen, 1929; 1 (Box 1)
  Illustration for the short story "Pad'ousy" within the anthology.
- Illustration for Vo třech princeznach, 1920s; 1 (Box 1)
- Illustration for Čarovná skřínka kouzelníka Merlína a jiné pohádky, 1933; 1 (Box 1)
  Čarovná skřínka kouzelníka Merlína a jiné pohádky
  http://hdl.handle.net/10079/bibid/7430906